welcome to voices with for Vicki I'm
joined by my good friend and colleague
Anderson Todd today we're going to
discuss the topic the young of cog high
cognitive science and the cogs eye of
young
so welcome Anderson it's great to have
you here again thank you John it's
always great to talk to you and so so
great to see you in this new era where
we live in a society of talk to you
televisions this is a natural mouth no
but thank you for having me
so Anderson could you just give
everybody sort of a brief introduction
to who you are some of my viewers have
no doubt already probably seen you and
I've had a couple of discussions you've
had a Q&A but it would be good if you
introduced yourself again sure so I'm
Anderson Todd if you haven't caught the
previous thing its Anderson is my first
name Thank You Anderson Cooper for
making my life easier Todd is my last
time I don't know if this was I don't
think my parents considered the jokey
effect of that reversal but but it has
rendered me nearly internet invisible
but it's my first time and to a my my
background
sort of academically is in cognitive
science I'm also trained as a registered
psychotherapist and I have a pretty wide
span of interest academically but at the
University I've previously taught in
cognitive science so I taught the
fourth-year capstone course on cognitive
science and consciousness I taught the
first half of the introductory conside
course and currently I teach the suite
of interdisciplinary courses in Union
Theory so that's a full year course on
young and then a half year course on the
hypotheses of the unconscious and then
in addition of that I'm a private
practice psychotherapist and I'm pretty
heavily influenced by depth psychology
although like many therapists I'm an
eclectic so that's sort of my wheelhouse
in general so you know due to the the
work of people like you know Jordan
Peterson and Joseph Campbell Young has
gone through something
resurgence and then you approach me with
this very interesting idea and something
I know you put a lot of thought into a
sort of Union are aspects of the
practice of cognitive science as opposed
to you know particular theoretical
claims made and within particular
theories but you there's something you
see some very important union elements
in the practice of cognitive science and
I think that's a very interesting topic
I'll briefly introduce what I take
cognitive science to be and and then
I'll let you I'll turn it over to you in
terms of the Union into the Union
interpretation of the practice of
cognitive science and then at some point
will will invert things and what can
cognitive science tell us about some of
the core Union constructs and processes
so I take it that many people will have
probably seen a lot of videos I've where
I've introduced the topic of cognitive
science so I won't I'll try not to make
this too long but for those of you who
are coming at this cognitive science is
born from the idea that the there are
many different disciplines that study
the mind neuroscience studies the brain
and it uses its own particular tools
gathers its own kinds of evidence etc
artificial intelligence studies
intelligence but difference to do it
doesn't a very different way from
neuroscience it tries to make machines
psychology studies the mind but it does
this largely by running experiments on
human behavior linguistic studies the
mind but it looks for patterns within
language and anthropology studies the
mind in so far is it works in
distributed cognition by doing
participant observation of culture so
each discipline studies the mind at a
different level and using different
tools and different theoretical entities
different types of data and is almost
like there are different countries
speaking a different language and the
problem with that is that it's very
likely that all these different levels
of the mind the brain level the
information processing level the
behavioral level the language using
level and the cultural level are not
independent from each other that they're
they interact
and constrain and affect each other in
powerful ways and so cognitive science
is born out of the idea about trying to
find a synoptic integration a way of
bridging between those so that those
various disciplines can more
appropriately talk to each other in an
insightful fashion mutually and
reciprocally inform and transform each
other the idea being that by having the
disciplines more appropriately bridge in
this way we can get make some progress
to getting how all these different
levels of the mind causally interact and
constrain each other and then cognitive
science is doing that they're trying to
afford the synoptic integration this
integrative picture precisely because
we're in a very important situation both
epistemic Lee and existentially we have
generated this powerful scientific
worldview that generates all these
explanations but we do not have a good
explanation of how we generate those
scientific explanations or the the
meaning we generate upon which those
explanations are dependent and so we
don't believe Emma 'kz ID but what that
means existentialism we don't belong in
that very world of you that has so much
normative authority over us and so the
the goal of cognitive science is to
figure out a way of resituated us back
within that scientific worldview so we
both have a more complete
epistemological picture and we can
alleviate some of the existential
distress people are feeling because
human beings and their meanings and such
do not seem to fit very readily within
the scientific purview so that's called
neuroscience in in five minutes I you
guys know I teach a I'll full your
course on this at the University of
Toronto so that don't take that to be
sort of complete or exhaustive but I
think it's good enough to give Anderson
some purchase to begin making his his
commentary yeah so you know as as we
sort of discussed in your previous video
you know both of the use both of these
subjects are
no science and and depth psychology
generally speaking have been sort of
fields of interest of mine for many
years yeah um and you know specific sort
of research and academic interest for
more than a decade now um but what sort
of increasingly became clear to me as I
was sort of doing work in both areas was
the extent to which they were in fact
kind of not just consonant but I I felt
well sort of specific sort of intro
theoretical material for each other
useful integer theoretical material so
you know when you're talking about the
kind of the synoptic integration right
the making these different countries of
discussion talking to each other one of
the things that that occurred to me
pretty early on I was interested in the
work of Thompson and Varela in talking
about oral phenomenology and it has sort
of long seemed to me that depth
psychology in some ways places a
particular kind of emphasis on the
phenomenology of psychological
experience and sort of clinical and
therapeutic experience right the
experience of life right and what it is
like to be and to to become and to
mature and so on and so forth and we're
sort of academic psychology has largely
it seems place that's focused on sort of
explaining mechanism in the circumstance
right in and zooming in on explicable
mechanism testable mechanism and
empirical findings in that way depth
psychology placed its emphasis more on
this phenomenological material more on
sort of the felt and lived experience
and there is I think for many people who
explore depth psychology in young this
this sense of a certain kind of lack
that lacks that underlying machinery
right that it talks about things and yet
it's hard to sort of connect that
phenomenological level with some kind of
underlining underlying machinery that's
sort of more consistent with what we now
know about the mind and brain function
and and so on and so forth but that also
the sort of more academic levels of
psychology off
and sort of fall a bit short in the
phenomenological sense it's hard to
figure out sometimes where some of these
findings and theories and someone's
connect to our sort of lived experience
so that gap was sort of increasingly
obvious to me which began to sort of
fuel a desire to bring it together and
when I started to look at things in
terms of normal phenomenology it began
to occur to me that this particular kind
of Western psychological
phenomenological practice that you find
in depth psychology might in some ways
be a kind of missing component for
making this stuff work within the
Western Canon hmm
right we're sort of a traditional neuron
phenomenology with Varela and Thompson
had had its emphasis right originally on
kind of a Buddhist approach right and
and that's fine but it leaves behind the
sort of a wealth of cultural material
and experience that is unique to sort of
the Western culture Western culture and
development right
and so bridging those things between um
part of it is that and we've talked
about this a little bit before but in
many ways I think some of the late
developments in yo the stuff that people
find sort of hard to understand but are
often they're attracted to it for this
sort of esoteric quality that it has so
when you young starts to get into things
like synchronicity and when he starts
particularly towards sort of the the end
of his career he becomes increasingly
interested in systems like alchemy and
that stuff is very very hard for for
people to get purchase on if they're
thinking in rational terms we have a
tendency to think alchemy as being a
sort of backwards proto chemistry that
we left behind but you sort of presents
this argument that in fact what alchemy
represented right especially for sort of
its its practitioners later and they're
quite explicit about it in places he's a
kind of inner work practice he calls it
a kind of master in yoga right yoga in
the fall well it sounds like that yoking
the connection to God and so you know he
talks about it as being sort of a
systematized set of methods that one
uses to do inner work
in much the same way as Eastern systems
do right and that's hard for us to wrap
our head around without without the
underlying machinery
likewise when people talk about
synchronicity and for for anybody that's
not familiar with the term or the police
album synchronicity is the is you lose
interest basically in meaningful
coincidence okay so the idea being that
you could have sort of symbolically
meaningful coincidences which happen to
you at certain kind of key moments of
development or of sort of personal
blockage right and the thing about that
stuff is it it skirts so closely to
things like parapsychology right where
we have a stock answer in you know in
sort of standard naturalist science of
saying well you know like probably those
oddball experiences that you're having
are a function of you selectively paying
attention to the probabilities and so on
and so forth but the thing that I was
jumped out about that stuff to me was
that that doesn't really negate the
experience itself right and and the
experience is in fact very often a
significant one regardless of what you
think about sort of the underlying
metaphysics of what's powering it um
and so people have a hard time basically
if they're from a naturalist between
accessing that kind of end of yo the
esoteric end but what increasingly
dawned on me and and I think you know in
in our conversations too which sort of
led to this is that in fact I think a
lot of what young is getting at and what
he would claim the alchemists we're
getting at is something that's actually
very very akin to the goals of cognitive
science okay that's really provocative
so you gotta unpack the work slowly okay
so so at the most basic level okay when
he's talking about things like
synchronicity he's essentially speaking
as we talked about before attempting to
bridge the mind-body problem right right
his notion of synchronization just to
make sure people understand that
mind-body problem is one of the core
problems in cognitive science this is
the problem that the the the way the
means given to us by the physical
sciences physics chemistry even some
sort of the more engineering Sciences
like computer science
give us some very powerful ways of
describing what's going on in in the
brain but that language does not seem
and notice we're talking about in
languages that language does not seem to
transfer well to describing the mind
especially important properties of
consciousness and so consciousness seems
to be something that many people find
very problematic to try and give it a
naturalistic explanation and and there's
all kinds of and and by the way this is
not some crackpot idea many people
within the heart of cognitive science
really important philosophers and
thinkers are there are I've come to the
clusion that we not might not be able to
come up with a naturalistic explanation
of consciousness many of them who think
we can come up with a naturalistic
explanation will admit that it's a very
famously a very hard problem right yeah
so for so for those that are familiar
with the hard problem you know it might
be easy to sort of look at you know the
wealth of you know bringing imaging
techniques and network mapping and like
the increasing sophistication we have on
the physical side with regard to
cognition and sort of hand-wave away you
know it's like yeah well consciousness
emerges from that but actually right as
David Chalmers the hard problem
demonstrates there's a really deep
philosophical problem and and you know
in some sense right the people that are
supporters of the hard problem and the
sort of irreducibility in some sense of
conscious experience will basically make
claims that land ascending in a kind of
dualistic situation right like a
Cartesian do list excision yeah where we
have these two fields and never the
twain shall meet or some kind of pan
psychism where some kind of like a
consciousness is a fundamental property
distributed throughout all of reality
and sometimes people put sort of a
quantum mechanics spin on that etc etc
yes so yeah you you show up on our
famously called this the world not it's
not just a problem about us when you try
and solve the problem of the
relationship between consciousness in
the brain you get into the sort of
fundamental grammar
of your metaphysics right yeah and I
think provided that you have a taste for
a certain level of ambiguity and
uncertainty that's a kind of delicious
mystery to contemplate right to think
about the hard problem and to really I
mean you know even even if you believe
that it's bridgeable just ramming your
head a little bit again it's the fact
that it's so hard to puzzle out can
himself be in my experience anyway I
kind of delicious mystery to contemplate
yes but you always very constrained with
this with with sort of the divide
between the subjective and objective
world why why was he concerned with it
um well if he was concerned with it I
think in part because you know although
he was not I think primarily recognized
as a philosopher right his his system of
thought is it's very philosophically
oriented he didn't just want to map
experience and fire and kind of clinical
intervention he wanted to to explain in
some importance as the nature of being
and because he was as concerned as he
was with the kind of mythic level of
experience the archetypal etc etc this
necessarily sort of started to vault him
into more mystical territory right you
start to get into the high reaches of
that stuff and sort of mystical
encounters with the self and all of a
sudden you're happening sort of
metaphysical confrontations with the
nature of being well right and so and on
top of that he had this long-standing
interest in things like synchronicity
and in parapsychology and the thing
about synchronicity right that that
triggers him particularly is the way
that seems to bridge that divide and
this is really active and the objective
yeah the striking way we're sort of
interior private subjective contents
seem to periodically constellation
external things in a shocking way these
moments of synchronicity have sort of
can have very transformative and
therapeutic effects on people that's
right yeah so there's a somewhat famous
you know anecdote that he tells about
having a client who was really locked in
on a rational framework and couldn't
couldn't kind of break through their
fixations and had had this dream that
they found quite affecting about
receiving a piece of jewelry kind of
turquoise scarab like an Egyptian scarab
beetle right right and in the middle of
having this conversation where they were
described in the dream you know young
describes hearing this sort of tap tap
tap at his window and he gets up and he
goes over to the window and when he
opens it up there's a rose chafer
which is a relatively for that part of
Switzerland uncommon kind of beetle but
it's like a greenish gold beetle which
flies into the window and so he catches
this thing in his hand and walks up to
his client and says here is your scarab
right and presents it to her and this
this sort of breakthrough of what was
seemingly a private inner material into
something that was external in a
meaningful way right the symbolic
concretization in some sense of its
inner blockage has this effect of sort
of shattering her fixation and then
allowing the the sort of therapeutic
work to proceed that's a relatively
commonly described thing people will
often feel sort of locked in when
they're doing certain you know certain
aspects of depth work but then they'll
have a synchronicity and there's
something about the way that that
seemingly bridges between their internal
experience in the world where they
experience a coincidence that really
throws them that makes them feel richly
connected to the world right so so you
know Jung is interested in trying to
figure out what accounts for this and
from his perspective it's like well it
seems to happen more often when people
are in states of intense emotional
activation when they're deeply fixated
and it's often it seemed to Tim
structured mythically now I should sort
of caveat in which is that his tendency
then is to he proposes basically a
return to a kind of earlier notion of
reality the Yunus mundus the oneworld so
he says there isn't the world of the
mind and the world of matter they're
really one thing they just have an
apparent division right and that the
archetypes from his perspective are
operating from this higher area and
they're sort of pushing simultaneously
into the two sides in a way that
right that then demonstrates directly
that there is a linkage between these
two worlds right so he was interested in
that level now the caveat is I don't
necessarily think it personally this is
where my work goes I don't think that
you necessarily have to interpret it in
such a metaphysically strong way for it
to be useful and significant and indeed
to contribute to a powerful explanatory
framework I think you can you can look
at those kinds of experiences and ask
yourself in a more naturalistic
framework well okay so what's going on
there if people are having that
experience is there a way that we can
talk about that that still gives us
something useful to say about bridging
this world because you know and this is
my first point I think a big part of
sort of this generation of cognitive
science and maybe cognitive science in
general is specifically working its way
towards that kind of you miss mundus
right right right yes and so how does
that link back to alchemy then okay well
so so I'll give you the short form
version and then I'll unpack this so you
know alchemy generally speaking people
tend to think of alchemy of sort of
chemistry's you know idiot kid brother
or something and that's a bit unfair you
know early early alchemy which traces
back at least as far as the first
century CE II and probably further if
you if you look at some of the sources
in the West you know comes as a sort of
rich alternate tradition as a Taric
tradition and it it
Hoover's up all kinds of influences so
it's closed so he associated with the
Gnostics mmm-hmm the Neoplatonic s--
right for reasons that we'll touch on in
more detail so so it's pulling in this
kind of alternate as at Eric view that
that permeated the west of the time but
was sort of at odds with the mainstream
a speciality of Christianity it was
periodically in in some cases in fact
there was a Pope I think in the 1300s
that straight-up declared it heresy so
it was often forced to operate
underground but lots of the premises
that alchemy is is based in especially
in their Neoplatonic roots I think have
have sort of a strong similarity to
popular science
for one okay so what's alchemy in the
main concerned with well it's concerned
with in the main the transformation of
metals specifically but the
transformation of matter and it's sort
of core concern is the transformation of
what it called the primal materia the
base material up through a set of
operations right to transform it into
some higher state of material being in
some cases that would be called the
Philosopher's Stone in some cases it was
the elixir in some cases the
Philosopher's Stone was not in fact the
goal state but rather was a kind of
intermediate transformative catalyst
agent you could then use to produce what
they called the philosophic gold so
that's like the classic form you hear is
turning lead into gold right base matter
led into high gold okay and that one
sounds pretty sort of abstract to us and
certainly there were some alchemists who
were concerned with that on the strictly
physical level so there were always
people that were interested in taking
lead and turning at an actual gold to
get rich and there were always people
who were concerned with what combination
of you know chemicals and operations do
I need to yield a potion of immortality
right like serve immortality so there
was always a relatively like a grounded
version of alchemy that ran but the
alchemists also saw their operations as
being spiritual operations so they saw
their work not merely as transforming
one form of matter into another form of
matter but rather in sort of advancing
matter up a chain of being right and
that draws pretty heavily from the
neoplatonist the idea is that matter
right so the alchemists are very
concerned with the notion of
self-organizing matter and the idea that
they're sort of midwifing it right that
the operations are or in some way
hastening or facilitating a set of
transformations that matter already
wants to go through that it wants to
transform itself on the chain so that's
really kind of interesting and then
another thing that the alchemists are
concerned with I'll tie this back around
in a sec you'll see them very often
being concerned with the production of a
homunculus
um now homunculus is the term of course
it turns up in psychology you get that
sensory homunculus
with the giant hands and mouth and
genitals and you get the the sort of
dreaded homunculus of infinite regress
right in right the monkey ler fallacy
but the monkey lists that they were
interested in producing was essentially
speaking like a little person that
wanted to produce life often by bottling
up sort of the the the core materials of
life so they would you know reap
reproductive tissue semen blood right
also based materials sealing in the land
that can produce life so here's the
basic link that I don't want to pitch
the alchemists are concerned with three
things overall they're concerned with
bridging the world of matter through to
the world of mind and spirit right so
they're they're concerned with sort of
showing the links that bridge those two
things together and just closing that
gap they are concerned with with the
production of thinking matter in a
certain sense right there the production
of life so in a sense sort of an
artificial intelligence a design stance
kind of approach right to losing stuff
and uh and in so far as they are
concerned with this spiritual transition
the thing about it is that they're not
just conducting those operations on the
world because they have a microcosm
macrocosm approach to this stuff as they
are transforming the substances the
world they are simultaneously affecting
those transformations in themselves so
it's it's a spiritual discipline
designed to refine transmute and make
more complex their own being in an
effort to heal themselves in some
fundamental way and to heal the world
simultaneously right these three things
are also what cognitive science is
basically concerned with cognitive
science is concerned with collapsing the
gap between world and the mind right to
make that a continuous thing we can show
that this transition that can occur and
that there's a continuity between those
two things it primarily approaches that
through a kind of design stance so
particularly with the early versions of
cognitive science right the idea is that
right under the sort of Aristotelian
idea that the person who makes a thing
knows the thing right if you can
deucey mind then you're gonna understand
the basic principles of mind right and
so you study through design you study by
making eye and similarly right the
production and the sort of experimental
approach towards creating things like a
monk ulis represents precisely that kind
of approach if you can make a mind if
you can achieve these things sort of in
in sort of experimental enacted form and
you know what you're talking about and
notably that has lots of sort of
metaphysical underpinnings like
self-organizing matter and stuff that of
organization emergence yep
self-organization and emergence and the
and yeah and then third of course you
know and this is not you know Universal
and cognitive science but I think one of
the underlying things that sort of
informs the ethos is the idea that once
we can once we can collapse that gap and
get the world connected back into a
units Mundus right and once we can
understand the mechanisms by which mind
operates we can then also intervene on
ourselves in some important
self-transforming way and that's
fundamental to what the alchemists are
doing when they're talking about in or
work the idea is working outside
yourself experimentally you are
simultaneously learning to transform the
states of your own being right so so the
fairly somewhat tongue-in-cheek but not
entirely tongue-in-cheek thing that I
like to say in class when I'm teaching
it is cognitive science is alchemy I see
cognitive science is in my opinion
actually a more apt inheritor of alchemy
than modern chemistry
which is largely jettisoned right the
the sort of secondary and interior and
subjective components that alchemy was
originally founded on and so you know
when the discipline splits when we get
chemistry coming off one side and we get
this coming off the other side sort of
depth psychology makes the claim to grab
that up but I actually think that depth
psychology because it's not done a lot
of the work in finding the underlying
ground it is in some sense abandoned the
side that chemistry was handling
originally right in fact I think
cognitive science is much closer to an
inheritor for that that particular
integrated aspect of that work that's
yeah and of course it's uh it's trying
to heal the world in a way - mm-hmm
there is much so so given that I mean
that you've made a you know that's a
plausible argument for an important
similarity what what insight about well
let's suppose there's insights to go
both ways but what insight I'm a
cognitive scientist what insight about
cognitive science do I get from seeing
it through the lens of it being a legacy
from alchemy like like what what what
what does that what how does that inform
and transform my conception or right
perhaps my practice of cognitive science
well um so you know one thing is at
least what you know what I'm thinking
about this it means that like I mean
when we talk about neuro phenomenology
right in the in the classic sort of
Thompson Varela fashion you know there's
sort of two sides to that you know the
idea is that what you want is highly
trained interest vectors people who are
capable of paying attention to their own
experience and their own cognition their
phenomenology in a way so that you when
you intervene on it with various sort of
techniques right you know whether you're
talking about sort of strictly psycho
technological techniques like meditation
or if you're talking about rights the
strict interventions like you know I'm
very interested in psychedelics and I'm
very interested in non-invasive brain
stimulation right these various ways of
intervening you need the sort of the
witnessing mind inside to be I have a
sufficient degree of training and
connoisseurship yeah that it can track
these small changes you need sort of to
be able to have the language to pick
that up when you're making the
intervention to try to bridge those two
things together right the fine details
that let you connect it um so so fastens
that is having that that sort of acuity
in your sort of ability to perceive and
describe and experience but the other
half a lot of the time of course is
about going back and looking at the
texts and the bodies of training around
people that have been doing that work
less with an eye to the neuro side and
more with an eye to the phenomenological
side so looking at texts of sort of
advanced meditative practitioners
right and and seeing in some way is
where the language that they're using
around the kinds of techniques that
they're using to alter their mind right
you take that stuff and you try to
examine it in close detail right
understand what it is and then you code
it back into mechanism right you try to
code it back into some sort of
understandable mechanism and there is
this back and forth this exchange which
allows you to refine possibly your
understanding of the mechanism and then
use that in turn to understand what's
going on so part of it is just that we
have this huge body of Western esoteric
doctrine right all these texts and like
we live in a world where those texts are
readily available to us in a way that
they have just never been historically
right this stuff was you know tight
tightly guarded and hard to get access
to it was you know hidden deliberate
right here so we have access to sort of
vast amounts of this stuff but what we
don't really have is something to put it
into dialogue with right so that's what
depth psychology tried to do was put it
into dialogue with with the psychology
and phenomenology of archetypal
experience and change and so on and so
forth I think that you can also of
course put those kinds of texts into
dialogue with cognitive science the same
way that you would with other kinds of
contemplatively
and that that that back and forth can
sort of clarify and hone both constructs
if you're willing to take seriously the
kinds of experiences that people have
written down in those tacks right you
have to sort of take them charitably in
at face value and and well face value
try to make sense of it in that way so
that's one thing but the other thing
about it that I think is particularly
long could you maybe could you give an
example of that first thing I'm sure
your second thing don't forget you're
second but maybe as you give a principal
give any trip okay so so one example
that I like to talk about and I
recognize that this is a high level high
level analogy like the broad analogy in
some ways but but it's useful for that
reason I think so one thing I wanted to
talk about is that sometimes they say
that the essence of the alchemical art
can be boiled down to a single notion
okay solve a at coagula
right so the principle of alchemy the
alchemical operation Solvay at coagula
was you dissolve and you solidify you
dissolve and you solidify your
sequentially going through this
operation but notice that it's all day
at coagula right and so so it's it's
it's and it's conjunctive the goal is
that eventually you're reaching a state
of sort of simultaneity to me that
sounds tremendously like integration and
differentiation so you know when you
integrate systems right you know tightly
and when you differentiate them you
bringing them apart but if you
simultaneously integrate them and
differentiate them you complexify them
and that specific complexification that
you get through running through that
process over and over and over again
right and then simultaneously you know
can be used in a sort of complexity and
dynamical systems to account for a kind
of complexification thinking about solve
a at coagula in that way for instance
has let me drill the drill into sort of
all kinds of techniques basically that
alchemists describe and to think about
them in terms of well what would we be
talking about if we were talking about
these things in terms of in terms of say
the integration and differentiation of
brain systems right residence right so
if for instance you're making the
assumption that you know yes okay
they're projecting into the outer
material to do their work right but that
fundamentally much of what we're talking
about it's a kind of psychological
experience then you can think about
solve a right dissolve and
complexification and you begin to
consider about areas where for instance
like mmm so I think about this in terms
of things like opponent processing
opponents and the transcendence of
opponent see I think about it in terms
of aspect shifting yeah I think about it
in terms of Michael afters reversal
theory and the idea of being able to or
you know like what's it's called the
Necker cube
oh yeah the Necker cube yeah the nectar
cube but what the specific anyway that
kind of aspect shifting right and to
some extent how
integration aspect of taking sort of
different streams of information and
integrating them right while
simultaneously differentiating them it
just provides a lot of explanatory
function and then I can kind of go into
the text and pull out specific
techniques and try to sort of run them
through that formula to see like what
would that produce hypothetically you
know what I mean so there's a chance
we'll talk about metastability well the
state in the brain in which the brain is
simultaneously integrating and
segregating and that that metastability
gives you all kinds of emergent
functions and how widespread and
important this is and it means so is it
possible to reinterpret what you're
saying that when the alchemists are
doing their practice it's like a
meditative practice that's actually
trying to engender a kind of medicine a
sort of pervasive metastability in the
brain yeah so one of the most useful
sort of concepts that I've put into my
own work more recently to frame this off
and connect the two is looking at
structural dissociation right I need a
neo dissociative theory so you know
we're used to thinking of dissociation
in a psychological sense often we use
dissociation strictly in pejorative
terms yeah when we talk about somebody
dissociating we talk about them tuning
out we talk about them sort of glazing
over from a clinical perspective I mean
you do look for that right so if you're
describing something you're talking
about a series and subjects with client
and and all the sudden they get like a
flat glazy faraway look often though
you've hit a nerve they've sort of
dissociated right and then serious cases
of dissociation people will lose access
to affect right they'll lose access to
feeling they may block a memory in
really serious cases of course they can
have shifts of identity and all kinds of
stuff and so we're used to thinking of
it as pathological and we're used to
thinking of it in pejorative terms but
of course it's the case that
dissociation actually is like a central
and necessary function to the way that
the mind and brain are working so we
dissociate when we're reading we
dissociate when we're daydream and
dissociation is integral to creative
process dissociation seems to occur on
the regular for instance when were
asleep and dreaming about which means
that areas that are normally in close
synchrony and communication across the
brain right drift into right there D
synchronized right so so this kind of
pattern of synchronizing and D
synchronizing right integrating and
differentiating is occurring all the
time as part of the regular functioning
of the brain of the mind and I argue
that that's sort of at the core of
processes of relevance realization in
some of the work I do right yes exactly
yeah yeah full disclosure I'm a non
Orthodox for vacant and I've worked with
John on enough stuff that we we have
lots of theoretical overlap because we
work together so a lot of this is gonna
be bouncing out of your work for sure
but one of the things that I like to
focus on in this respect is so the work
of Raz 2007 weight hypnosis on footing
right how did they do it well they did a
hypnotic induction on suggestible
subjects but they did hypnotic induction
and what they did was they had people
basically lose access to literacy right
and in so doing they allowed people to
cut through the Stroop effect the
automaticity of the Stroop effect right
right so when I talk about the strip
effect the thing that's really
interesting to me about Stroupe right is
first off it sort of already breaks
through the unit of bias right it sort
of implies multiple streams of
processing necessarily yeah of course it
does but the interesting thing about the
razzle at work is that what they showed
is that right this minor intervention of
words and a certain kind of attention
could dissociate right a module of
processing that's normally so tightly
integrated with automaticity that we
actually can't consciously interview
most the robust effects right right it's
a whole cottage industry and it's a
really powerful effect so okay so if
sort of hypnotic and trance practice can
do this thing where it can take a module
and sort of dissociate it out from
regular functioning and if we know that
dissociative processes are sort of
occurring regularly in the brain anyway
part of what I'm suggesting is is
happening in something like health
chemical practice is
that projective psycho technologies are
being used to selectively dissociate
aspects of the mind and that has a few
sort of effects one any two modules that
are previously integrated that start to
dissociate from each other there's a
certain point at which they're going to
start to experience each other as as
other right right right yeah yeah right
so so when you experience certain kinds
of dissociation right when people are
Sadie realized or depersonalized right
you know they get a certain amount of
dissociation and then the the component
that drifts apart from the main portion
that is sort of supporting their
consciousness this outside chunk scenes
alien and weird we can see this when
people for instance if you see people
that have their corpus callosum levered
and they'll get alien hand syndrome
right describe it yeah sure
alien hand syndrome I can't remember the
front instrum but it's alien hand
syndrome it's the term so I'm you know
when they pioneered a set of surgeries
for severing the corpus callosum the
band of connective communicative tissue
that links together the hemispheres
tightly and they did it originally to
stop certain kinds of sort of runaway
seizures right and it could be pretty
effective and initially speaking when
they did these surgeries on people they
were like oh they seem to be behaving
just fine but it turns out that you know
if you look at the work of gaz amiga and
people like that we're looking in the
70s there are a bunch of things that you
can do that demonstrate that actually
the hemispheres are operating almost
sort of independent consciousnesses they
have sorts and I recommend Ian
McGilchrist book the master news
emissary yes yes absolutely that's a
great book in some cases of this corpus
callosotomy you'll get what's called
alien hand syndrome and what happens is
that the non-dominant hand starts to
take on autonomous behavior so people
will go to open a door and the hand will
close it or they'll pick something I'm
not going to do this because I'll knock
a coffee all over myself but the hand
will like a SWAT planes over their hand
sometimes the hand will help them like
it seems to take on a seemingly kind of
atomic autonomous thing now in and of
itself you know we're like
well that's weird but I think the thing
that you have to consider is it's like
okay well if we're assuming for a second
that the non-dominant hemisphere is
what's operating this the non-dominant
hemisphere is still doing a lot of
information processing yeah no small
thing to to see that somebody else is
opening the door and close it that
requires a lot of right information
processing I think of it sort of the
same I say no to myths of blindsight
yeah right where there's a certain
amount of processing so um so there are
cases like this where there's sort of
physical change right which then can
cause autonomous behavior and we see
that as as weird and highly anomalous
but my point is when these systems
dissociate normally right under normal
conditions they already other in that
same way right the behavior of the arm
others to us it's outside alien hand is
outside our regular consciousness it's
still obviously doing things that
require cognitive processing but we
don't have access to it and our agency
doesn't connect to it it just seems to
behave in this it's connected to us but
also it's not us right it's not yeah I
would connect that through to all kinds
of comparable kinds of psychological
experiences that people have like the
third man phenomenon or apparitions of
dead people see the recently dead quite
often like it's surprisingly common but
also you know things that are
considerably sort of more in a sense
mundane like hearing voices which is
very very common yeah especially under
conditions like sleep deprivation um and
of course as I like to talk about dreams
yeah right where the event is I think as
most people would consider it anyway the
event is internal to the brain it's
internal to the mind right and yet there
are sort of complex actors in the space
that we don't have direct control over
we are not deciding on more in lucid
dreaming right even well yeah even more
in lucid dreaming but in regular
dreaming - yeah you know you know we
have a dream we don't set the stage we
don't decide what's happening
right and even in lucid dreaming one of
the things that's so weird about it is
you do
have more control but you don't perfect
control
no and things push back on you and
surprise you yeah right so if we're
assuming that these are sort of normally
integrated portions that right
dissociate and other right then we can
sort of look at it and say okay this is
a regular part of the functioning of the
mind right is that periodically it goes
to these integration and disintegration
cycles I think that using a psycho
technology like alchemy essentially
allows you to somewhat take control of
that process because it projective Lee
and then you manipulate it and then that
and then that is reaper sieved right and
so there's an idea somewhat popularized
by Stanovich which is the narayan
bootstrap and i stumbled across this I
think it was in the robots dilemma I was
where he talks about that
well that's rebellion robots rebellion
yeah
so the Navi and bootstrap comes out of
the work of Otto Neurath and basically
you know it's looking at the question of
you know the Ship of Theseus right so
classic Ship of Theseus is well you have
a boat and you replace the mast and you
replace the boards and you replace the
figurehead masthead whatever your place
little pieces is it's the same boat and
the answer is yes because a boat is a
pattern but the question that Otto
Neurath got out was like okay but let's
say that you want to replace a piece of
the boat let's say that you want to
replace a board you know pry a board up
how do you do that without damaging all
the connected material right and when
Stanovich looks at he's looking at
specifically like propositional beliefs
so let's say you have an erroneous
belief and it's interlocked together
with a bunch of other things
how can you sort of get a bootstrap to
get yourself off the deck long enough to
be able to pry the rotten board out and
replace it while while not sort of
sending the rest of your belief system
haywire right so that's how Stanovich
uses in this concept of the irathient
bootstrap I think that these sorts of
projective psycho technologies
essentially speaking are using
techniques of dissociation to isolate
out components of our functioning so
that we can operate on them
independently but also so that we can
bring to bear the machinery that we
normally used interact with other people
to interact with portions of ourselves
right right yeah that's interesting
that's interesting so I just make sure
we didn't lose the thread this is a good
example of the first point you were
making about the way in which cognitive
science is sort of a modern-day version
of alchemy and that one of the things we
can get from this is we can use
cognitive science to go back and re
appropriate because of that deep kinship
we can use cognitive science to go back
Andrea propriate these outcome
alchemical texts and practices within a
cognitive scientific framework and
perhaps regain their efficacy or perhaps
even enhance their efficacy yes yeah and
so you know so you know if I want to
guess make it move each way you know the
idea is that of course reinterpreting
the sort of depth psychological take on
alchemy as a form of inner work using
cognitive science material like neo
dissociation like mutual modeling right
like certain kinds of dynamical systems
and network theory right that kind of
stuff can bring an appreciation to that
material that lets you get into the text
and have a clearer sense of what this
might mean at a more mechanistic level
like what are we talking about in terms
that science can
congratz can understand but also it's
the case that having done so there are
specific techniques that emerge in
alchemy right that when you when you go
through the body of those techniques
that has really interesting sort of
reverse bearing back on the
understanding of some concepts within I
think a cognitive science please okay so
so one that I try to communicate to
people and it's difficult to communicate
but there's an equation that I sometimes
like to make so so sometimes for
cognitive science students one of the
equivalences and I don't want to I don't
want to literal eyes this too much but
we can play with it a little bit is to
connect together the capital S self in
Jungian thinking right
the kind of notion of fundamental
framing with relevance realization so if
we you know look at these various
components of the Union psyche okay yes
we have the the ego our self conception
and we have the shadow we have all that
material but some we're sort of above
all of that and yet somehow you know it
is it is both the totality and the
center of all of that is this notion of
the Union itself and experiences of the
self when people describe experiences
itself often are coated in religious
terms yes right so people have religious
experiences and right but the idea in in
depth psyche and Union thinking would be
that really what you're doing is having
an account of itself this central
component if you think of that for a
second and you're like okay well what
would it really mean to have an
encounter with the portion of your mind
that is the portion right the portion of
your mind portion or the aspect of your
mind that is the ground from which all
other mental events well what would it
be like to make contact with something
that does not experience opposites in
some important sense and that you know
is pre categorical in some important
sense and pre syntactic and pre
semantics right something that is the
generator of meaning but doesn't itself
it kind of like uh doesn't fall within
the like it it's generating the framing
that makes meaning possible but it's not
any of the content within that that kind
of timing
yeah so if we think about that from just
like from the phenomenological side the
point that you makes about the encounter
with the self being indistinguishable
from the encounter with God right is
that when we encounter this portion of
the self for one thing it responds to
sort of symbolic language and tends to
speak in these terms
not because it's imprecise but because
the kind of information that has can
only get through to us in these
concentrated massive you know sort of
mystical symbolic bursts it's just the
only way we can access that stuff is
what it breaks through into phenomena we
experience it in that way but you know
if you if you sort of consider in the
other direction it's like Oh
okay so if we can somehow get our
consciousness in touch with this this
sort of fundamental ground of cognition
this thing is the maker of all worlds
yeah relevance realization in that way
right so this is a direct encounter with
it right so this is a converging
argument without a lot of arguments I
make about there's sort of a spiritual
significance when we try to relate to
and enter into symbolic communication
with the you know the the machinery of
relevance realization yes yeah and and
certainly you know like I shared that
idea to me the the you're adding
something to it
your what you're doing here is that I
didn't do is you're bringing in a lot of
the archetypal phenomenology that the
Union Theory has and a lot of the work
around that so use what you're saying
like am I getting this argument correct
is we can understand a particular kind
of experience we can grasp its
phenomenology in in in terms of well
first all we can understand it
ontological II as a relationship to
relevance realization a massively
recursive on on all the stuff I talked
about in the series but that that
relationship has a phenomenology that
can be very well explicate Adana lou
sedated by making use of the union
framework is that is that what you're is
that what your point yeah yeah and and
in fact in many ways the Union and depth
psychological frame will work represents
a somewhat you know I have a lot of
respect for these people but it never
lasts represents a somewhat imperfect
and slightly blunt version of that right
and that the original texts in fact if
you can go back and start to get at them
in a certain sense can give you sort of
phenomenological signposts on that
experience that are remarkably powerful
and often counterintuitive example of
that you saw humans sure so okay so one
thing that
I have that I'd like to talk about in
this respect is you know very often it's
the case that the the sort of interior
version of the alchemy that's championed
by young and people focuses on the idea
that some of the standard alchemical
operators and substances and things are
representative of affective and
cognitive states right so for instance
salt okay salt in the alchemical corpus
is often related to weirdly bitterness
instead of salt but ever like bitter yes
right okay and um and so you know there
will be things in these texts where
they're like you know look if you have
such and such and such state what it
requires now is this to catalyze an in
transform it okay so strictly from a DEP
psychological perspective right there
there's an idea in which you know
something like bitterness having a note
of bitterness in your experience being
slightly bitter about something it's not
someplace that you want to stay but
having a note of bitterness in your
experience also segues into having a
more complex and integrated emotional
state than was previously available to
you right and I know that you and I have
both shared the idea in the past that it
would be difficult in some ways for me
to have a deep and engaged human
relationship with somebody that I felt
hadn't experienced some degree of
tragedy yes some degree of grief yep
yeah having a sense of tragedy in the
world and I'm pretty optimistic person
but nevertheless having some contact
with that with that aspect of reality is
just important to facilitating what
depth of character
now we think about some of the complex
emotions that people have that we
develop as time goes on right little
kids don't have a concept of the
bittersweet hmm right right right
little kids can't pick up say the nuance
this is almost the opposite of
alexithymia they can't pick up the
nuance a in different states of
nostalgia but there's such a thing as a
rancid nostalgia and there's such a
thing as like actually a warm and
pleasant form of nostalgia great for
nostalgia there are lots of these
relatively complex feelings that that we
have that we consider part of our
maturation right that exists as
is an integrative state the alchemists
talked at some length about the
introduction of bitterness to transform
other kinds of affective and cognitive
states right mm-hmm so and the thing
that I have said a few times have cost
around and maybe is again I'm being a
bit of a provocateur but you know the
fact that we can sin aesthetically and
otherwise dynamically interconnect
different portions of our processing and
our cognition right because the the same
thing that basically blocks us from
being able to like raw power crunch
through that because of competitor eel
explosion to explain what's going on in
the connectome it also means that the
states of interconnection which are
possible within the mind and the brain
have not been exhausted by human
experience right like part of the
complexification of our cognitive and
emotional states is the simultaneity the
the synthesis right and right the
transcendence of opponent see in some
cases of different states that that then
leveraged themselves up in a higher in
higher States so like if you think of a
Praja for sure you've talked about I
thought well I don't think I've talked
about it in this series awakening for
the meaning crisis for sure but I'll
just describe it sort of briefly here
there's different course different
traditions have different meanings
attached to it but one is progeny is a
state that a for sometimes affords or is
identified with wisdom because it's a
state of non-dual awareness you have
sort of as far as you could possibly go
inward with meditation and as far as you
could possibly go outward with
contemplation but you're having them
simultaneously at the same time and this
is this is actually the state that's
most sought-after because it is the
state that is most affording of
self-liberation self transformation
right okay so essentially speaking what
you're talking about there is a state of
cognition partly of sort of construal
partly of identity right it's got an
altered state kind of character to it
talking about taking two states that are
themselves relatively difficult to
cultivate right and doing so in a way
that allows you to gradually integrate
them into some higher state that in some
sense transcends that's the bread and
butter of alchemy this ascendance of
opposite stuff right and the unification
of opposites is sort of central to their
discipline right and so they have huge
bodies of sort of literature that we
describe in some way right so when you
look for instance at the alchemical
symbolism when you look at the the
divine union of the Sun and the moon
right so you'll get the images of the
king and the queen in various states of
light union or coitus right then being
buried together and then emerging as a
kind of mystic hermaphrodite right a
figure that partakes of the solar and
the lunar and male and female and is a
kind of divine right saying that
transcends this is all the kinds of
symbolism that they use to talk about
precisely this kind of like cultivating
different states and then and then being
able to synthesize them together and
they also have a really well sort of
articulated set of taxonomies and
operations for different states of
synthesis and what it takes to
synthesize things so to ground this out
again okay
there's an example that I've heard you
sometimes when you're talking about
aspect shifting where you talk about the
mother-in-law who um sees as being
boorish yeah yeah yeah okay and the idea
is that there's a kind of aspect shift
that can happen where you can undertake
a charitable reinterpretation where
first you're like well they're boorish
and they're loud and they're pushy but
then you flip it and you're like well
but they're forthright and they're
honest and they're direct and they're
right there's there's a way to
charitably reinterpret that to flip the
aspect on similarly when you're talking
about the unification of opposites in
depth psyche and then alchemy generally
right very often you're dealing with
pairs of opposites and part of the
manipulation that you're going through
psychologically is a set of aspect
manipulations to make them less directly
opposed so you know black and white you
know those seem pretty opposite to
people but are male and female actually
opposite
in that way some people would say so
they'd be like yes men and women are
opposites and that's where you get this
like men are from Mars Women are from
Venus you know the gender war stuff but
there are obviously ways of looking at
it were you like well not only are they
not opposite in the sense that black and
white or black and not black are
opposite right but that they they really
actually have a great deal of
commonality between them right and being
able to go through that kind of shift
around your thinking with it being able
to pick up on the commonalities and so
on and so forth is part and parcel of
being able to bring them together
without getting a kind of categorical
rejection or repulsion how come he's
full of this stuff and so yeah yeah I I
could go down this rabbit hole forever
and it won't not today anyway
yeah so they're sort of bodies of
material there that I think have a lot
to tell us if we can plumb them
charitably and with this particular I
not only pls but train us the idea is we
could what I'm what I'm hearing you say
is it could train us so that we could
fine tune our phenomenology and a
phenomenological interventions in ways
that would themselves be revealing but
also in ways that would be more
theoretically consonant with some of our
cutting-edge constructs from cognitive
science and therefore we could get those
two domains to be talking to each other
more readily is that fair yeah that's no
that's that's exactly right
um and you know again I toss us off when
I say like because you know any two
areas can theoretically be connected
together and in a bunch of different
ways in the mind and they can
theoretically you can have sort of
different kinds of synesthesia I think a
lot of development is precisely that
kind of complexification towards these
increase states of synthesis and right
the fine-tuning of categories and stuff
that we see in like Piaget but but part
and parcel of that is that like this
tells us a ton about affective
development cognitive
development it tells us a lot about
altered states because you know part of
the problem of the taxonomy of altered
states is also that it's like how do we
fit a framework well if you can connect
things together and that yields an
altered state then the potential state
space of all that stuff is enormous and
so partly looking at it in this
particular way right it gives a kind of
a framework a training framework where
you can begin to consider that and stop
trying to sort of exhaust the space I
mean yeah
so that's really cool so there's a sense
in which we could use an archetypal
phenomenology in conjunction with sort
of more standard you know Marlowe Ponte
whether that's what Evan wasn't even tom
says that's right big-nose together and
then part of the thing we could do with
the complexification is it's not it's
also complexification that is can be
reflective it can be confess off'
ocation that gives us an increasing
fluency of how we are relating to and
being coupled to you know all of these
sub current unconscious cognitive
processes the relevant realization
machinery etc etc that have both a
important cognitive function for us but
also a spiritual significance to us is
that yes that's right
so there's sort of there's kind of three
you know outcomes in that sense right
you know on one hand it it yes it gives
us that that sort of increased language
and grammar and training the breathing
we're also transforming ourselves I mean
that's central to the alchemical
property and you know looking at this
and I should to go back and say that was
precisely Murdock's point too about the
aspect shift with the mother-in-law
right at the point was it's not just
that you reframe the mother-in-law the
the daughter-in-law or the other way
around such as Yuri friend the
daughter-in-law the mother-in-law has to
reframe herself that's right she has to
she has to say well wait how what kind
of person was are there because I was
miss framing them and then what kind of
person do I need to be in order to now
properly relate to this aspect shift yes
you can't keep the two separate from
each other that's right and that applies
this again is sort of central to the
alchemical as above so below you know
cause a macrocosm principle you know as
you're doing this kind of categorical
coldly but if you're exploring it it's
come out for a second dose and as you're
doing this kind of what cattle as you're
doing this kind of this kind of
categorical transformative work right
with your own cognition your own effect
and so on and so forth right because of
the as above so below
I could cause a macrocosm principle you
know you can be doing it theoretically
right and you're gonna be just talking
about theoretically but if you're doing
it if you're doing it as a practice then
simultaneously you are indeed affecting
your perception and experience of the
world but also right in your
relationship to the categories and
people within the world in that way but
also you're talking about altering your
internal Constitution you're talking
about you know doing essentially
therapeutic work in that sense which is
to say that like there are plenty of
pieces of your mind at any given time
that are working at cross-purposes to
each other they get in your way and it
causes you you know ego you problems
like why can't this piece of my mind
behave why can't that piece of my mind
behave
lots of therapeutic technique if it
comes out of you know somewhat
psychodynamic frame is concerned with
attempting to sort of improve relations
and communication between look like to
pay them getting justice thank you yes
yeah well and so that's the thing you
know part of this is you're instituting
a kind of you know set of techniques
that enables you to transform the
community of yourself which
simultaneously transforms the community
of the world because they're all running
on the same machinery internal
distributed cognition as well yes yes
absolutely because you know at the end
of the day it would be the homunculus II
to think that it doesn't that your mind
doesn't in some sense break down to some
components that have less functionality
than the top level right and so there
are sort of Demi people I mean that is
sort of central to the this is central
to the the psychodynamic idea is that
you have these sub components and they
might not be as smart as you
and as skilled as you and as whatever
but like to some extent they have there
perspective in their own goals and if
those people are on the same page if
there's miscommunication and if they're
at each other's throats like alien hand
this is going to cause you real problems
so doing this kind of work in this way
has you know it has theoretical impact
but also we're talking about
simultaneously changing your experience
in the world and your experience of the
self in the connection between those
things that's amazing well I think a
question comes to mind that I've sort of
been holding off on this is the reverse
the case our people and so obviously I'm
gonna fall into this category are people
who are practicing cognitive science qua
cognitive science doing a kind of crypto
alchemy unawares thought of it that way
yes
okay can you can you say a little bit
more than just you you've you've out
alchemy the alchemists to explain the
obscure bunions of yet more obscure uh
if you're so deeply to the crypto you
don't even know yeah in a sense I think
so I mean you know if you if you
subscribe to this particular
interpretation of what's going on in
chemical work right then yeah in a sense
what cognitive science is attempting to
do I mean is it's the same aims it's the
same it's the same aims and of course
you know lots of cognitive sciences
aren't going to take this particular
kind of phenomena logically you know
focused approach to things right lots of
people are primarily concerned with sort
of the the biomechanics and sort of the
you know the production of the AI as a
you know as a mechanical production and
so on and so forth right but that's a
bit like saying you know the people that
were just concerned with producing the
monkey less and didn't give it in but
the philosophic they were just very
homunculus focused if I can just get
this matter to produce a thinking being
damn it
then I will understand what's happening
well that's what we're talking about um
and I guess that brings me back around
to the synchronicity piece so you know
synchronicity is sort of the odd man out
if you're trying to well I thought I've
always found it as you know
deeply problematic well me too and not
least because I've experienced so this
is the fit right you have an experience
of this kind and you know if you I think
are sort of flexible around thinking
about it you slosh back and forth in
your interpretations right it's sort of
it forces the improbability the seeming
improbability of it begins to try to
force interpretations on you right right
and there's a kind of like there's an
there's a breakthrough mysticism that
comes with just having it because you're
like what are the odds of this like it
seems so meaningful and significant and
related to me and you can get really
hung up or you can go one of two
directions on that you can either reduce
it and say whatever this is just like a
garbage artifact of my cognitive biases
right or you can be like oh this is very
clear evidence that the universe is as a
meaningful narrative place that is
trying to deliver me personalized
messages and honestly I think that
sometimes there's utility and value to
moving into one or those other states
right you know despite the fact that
from the naturalistic framework you know
the universe is not a narrative is our
current mission right nevertheless
sometimes feeling that the universe is
narrative can have a utility provided
that you don't get fixated all right but
but the other thing is this it's like
looking at you know without so being
sort of you know metaphysically agnostic
about what's happening a little bit
right and just being like okay if the
experience is however that encounters
with the self encounters with the deep
self which are are sort of mystical
encounters with something that seems
divine and it's productive abilities as
that's right has this ability to break
through this gap and make it seem as
though things are that I'm meaningfully
connected to the world and some
important sense and then I'm producing
meaning in the world and stuff that to
me sounds like a very direct experience
of relevance realization occurring
outside the conscious bounds but in this
uh Turley breakthrough way oh that's
like your mind is constellated the world
in some really important sense yeah and
that's
the system gives you one of those
basically I think as a kind of like like
throwing a long link of insight right to
break you through especially out of sort
of a state of paralysis if the right if
you're in a state of depressive
paralysis or - and if relevant
utilization is ultimately a trans Jets
being co-created yes the dynamic
coupling between the dynamics of the
brain of the dynamics of the world
attributing agency to either one of
those is kind of misplaced in some way
right right so the world is much
responsible for that that relevant that
the emergence of that relevance as the
brain is is that partially what you're
here yes yeah and so in that sense right
one other creep anissa t as an enacted
symbolic apprehension of trans Jack
tivity that's a really interesting
reinterpretation oh wow that's really
cool yeah so that's kind of that's where
I've landed on it now that doesn't mean
that I never entertained the you know
whatever probabilistic error
interpretation I never entertained B of
course it turns out that it's on the
mystical Savior interpretation but or
I'm super special thank God I was
beginning to feel like I wasn't um you
know typically in fact when you know
people can get kind of hooked for lack
of a better term on it right there's a
you can get into tennis gets a tie pole
tumble where you start to you know it's
over experience pattern right and so
synchronicity can run away with people
but when it's one of these like Dirk
Brockie kind of things where
breakthrough experiences yeah what
you're getting is a direct point of
contact with the way that you and the
world and the systems of meaning are
both emergent and co-created and that
you have a kind of identity yet not
identity with the ground of the thing
that makes you and the world and fits
them together it's a direct and
symbolically compressed experience of
that thing it makes you feel special and
important because it shows you that the
world is thinking you and you are
thinking the world yeah that's really
cool and in that sense at the high level
like it's about
the control that I think that in that
that doesn't take anything away from in
the same as it doesn't really take
anything away from it in my experience
if you have a kind of encounter with the
mystical and you interpret it as a self
and you interpret the self as the
underlying machinery of your of your
cognition to me for some people that's
going to be like I'll what a drag that
means that I didn't in fact make contact
with the creator of the universe but but
to me I'm like but yeah you did yes you
did you had contact with the creator of
the universe and it's completely allowed
it's inside the rules right it doesn't
require you don't have to break any of
the basic rational rules to do it it
just means that you have succeeded in
getting some point of contact with the
thing that creates the only universe
you're ever going to experience and and
you within it you know so an altered
state of identity an altered state of
construal an altered state of effect and
so on and so forth anyway yeah that's
we're coming to where we should probably
close this off yeah but so you've
mentioned this to me before you a lot of
the stuff and you've now like a lot of
the insights were novel to me today so
thank you for that but you have
mentioned to me in the past that you're
putting this basically into a book of
some kind understanding and what's the
progress and state of that book and when
you foresee it coming to mom well so so
the the emergence of code 19 has had
obviously some unusual impacts on that
in some ways it has been in some ways
it's accelerated things yeah you know
we're we're in fact I've sort of maybe
the alchemical comparison it's like
we're all sealed in the Alembic right
now so people's psychological state is
really set to boil because we all have a
cork in it and we can't go out you know
I've sometimes called this the
involuntary monastery our whole culture
has shipped off to the involuntary
monastery um so in some ways the the
theoretical work around it has been and
also I'm sealed in here with my library
yeah we're gonna have thousand books in
here that need reading
and so so yeah so that's accelerator
somewhat i'm hoping to sort of I've
begun sort of writing out some of the
chapter outlines and structuring things
but I'm hoping to sort of attack it in
earnest starting later this month and
the working title which is bit glib is a
shape-shifting a practical guide but
yeah it'll connect together a bunch of
this stuff it'll connect together young
and Corbin and cognitive science and a
lot of my new dissociative theory it my
work on lucid dreaming altered states
you're also going to be writing
something for the anthology that Chris
and I are putting together on inner and
outer dialogues yeah yeah so that'll in
fact probably those two things will
themselves be in dialogue so yeah I'm
gonna be writing about young and Corbin
and the imaginal and some of the aspects
of inner work particularly the you know
things related to what we've talked
about here probably not with exactly
this framing and I probably also will
touch to some extent on on some of the
sort of triangulations of of Corbin and
Jung against newer neo unions like
wolfgang gingrich i had sort of some
interesting critiques of the imaginal
and of the image as the focus for doing
this kind of work so yeah so and when
that's pretty soon too I think I'll
probably be reading that in May yes yeah
well that's great um well thank you so
much that was really really cool I like
I was really intriguing and a lot of the
insights are really really
thought-provoking and I think they're
they're like they're they have at least
initial theoretical plausibility I'm
really looking forward to writing this
yeah oh well I would like you to read it
give it a look over before I send it
yeah ya know
clarifying a lot of the stuff has been
good I mean some of it has built on
lectures I've given for classes in the
last few years and so going back and
sort of extracting that material and
refining it I'm trying to get it in a
more end-to-end way obviously I'm sort
of talking shooting from the hip a bit
here but I have whatever local sources
and references that need sorting out to
sort that out but yeah I'm looking
forward to it too I've been doing lots
of work in the area and
well for anybody that is interested I've
been recording because all lectures are
online lectures now so I've been
recording some of the final classes for
some of my own courses on the subject I
released the first half of the alchemy
lecture that I did for my own class out
for people just four hours long but I'll
send you the the link to that for the
second half is kind of mid production so
I'll send you that link to and you can
if people are interested they can check
that out great ok I'll get all the links
that I can granderson we might put in a
link for the Stroop effect for those
because we didn't really explain it but
we'll put on a link so people can check
that out and I'm sure all I know I'm
very confident you and I are going to
talk again thank you very much for
coming on voices with verve a key it was
a great pleasure thank you John Alma's
pleasure